Inventory of the Lucille Nichols Patrick papers, 1901-1982
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Lucille Nichols Patrick papers
1901-1982
Patrick, Lucille Nichols
02351
2.70 cubic feet (6 boxes)
University of Wyoming. American Heritage Center.
Papers of a historian of the Cody, Wyoming, area.
Biography of Lucille Nichols Patrick and James Calvin Nichols
Lucille Nichols Patrick (1924-2003), an author and artist, was born in Illinois, but settled in the Cody, Wyoming, area, where her father, James Calvin Nichols had business interests. Among her books were "The Best Little Town by a Dam Site: or Cody's First 20 Years," "The Candy Kid: James Calvin 'Kid' Nichols, 1883-1962," and "Caroline Lockhart, Liberated Lady, 1870-1962" (published under the name Lucille Patrick Hicks). She also edited "The Park County [Wyoming] Story" under the name Lucille N. Hicks.
James Calvin Nichols (1883-1962) was a professional wrestler known as "The Kid" and the "Candy Kid" in his youth. After working for a paper company in Chicago, Illinois, he established his own plywood and veneer business around 1920. He owned plywood and related businesses in Illinois, Georgia, Mississippi and Wyoming, where he established Nichols Industries in Cody. He bought the Diamond Bar Ranch near Cody around 1926.
Scope and Content
The Lucille Nichols Patrick materials include correspondence; files compiled for her history of Cody, Wyoming; manuscripts "The Candy Kid", "The Best Little Town by a Dam Site", and "Caroline Lockhart, Liberated Lady"; research on Cody history, Buffalo Bill Dam on the Shoshone River, and James C. Nichols; prints of thirteen pen and ink drawings of ranch life by Patrick; and research materials and photographs of Wyoming pioneer cemeteries.
The James Calvin Nichols materials include correspondence (1932-1962), much of it with his lawyer, Milward L. Simpson of Cody; legal documents (1903-1949); and reminiscences, mostly concerning hunting trips.
Access Restrictions
There are no access restrictions on the materials for research purposes, and the collection is open to the public.
Related Materials
There are no known other archival collections created by Lucille Nichols Patrick at the date of processing.
Acquisition Information
The collection was received from Lucille Nichols Patrick (Hicks), 1967-1982
Access Terms
Nichols, James Calvin, 1883-1962.; Simpson, Milward L.; Shoshone Project.; Ranches -- Wyoming -- Park County.; Hunting -- Wyoming.; Ranches in art.; Dams -- Wyoming -- Park County.; Cattle trade -- Wyoming -- Park County.; Cody (Wyo.) -- History.; Park County (Wyo.) -- History.; Buffalo Bill Dam (Wyo.) -- History.; Wyoming -- History -- 1890-1918.; Wyoming -- History -- 1919-1945.; Wyoming -- History -- 1946-1999.; Diamond Bar Ranch (Wyo.); Legal documents.; Reminiscences.; Galley proofs.; Authors, American.;; Hicks, Lucille N.; Hicks, Lucille Patrick.; Nichols, James Calvin, 1883-1962 -- Papers.; Patrick, Lucille Nichols -- Best little town by a dam site.; Patrick, Lucille Nichols -- Candy kid.
Agriculture and Natural Resources; Ranching; Water and Water Rights; Social Life and Customs; Sports and Recreation; Technology; Wyoming
Container List
- Series I. Creative Works by Lucille Nichols Patrick
  - Sub-series 1. Manuscripts
    - The Best Little Town By a Dam Site!, undated (Box 1)
    - The Best Little Town By a Dam Site! Unedited, undated (Box 1)
    - Best Little Town By a Dam Site - Excerpts, undated (Box 1)
    - Candy Kid, undated (Box 2)
    - Candy Kid - Drafts, undated (Box 2)
    - Candy Kid - Galley Proofs, 1969 (Box 2)
    - Caroline Lockhart: Liberated Lady, 1870-1962, undated (Box 2-3)
    - Caroline Lockhart: Liberated Lady, 1870-1962 - Addenda, undated (Box 3)
    - Caroline Lockhart: Liberated Lady, 1870-1962 - Footnotes, undated (Box 3)
    - Caroline Lockhart: Liberated Lady, 1870-1962 - Bibliography, undated (Box 3)
  - Sub-series 2. Other Creative Works
    - Articles By Lucille Nichols Patrick, 1966-1967, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Artwork: Prints of Pen and Ink Drawings of Ranch Life, undated (Box 3)
- Series II. Research Materials
  - Best Little Town By a Dam Site - Notes, undated (Box 3)
  - Biographical: Bob Rumsey, undated (Box 3)
  - Biographical: Frank Blackburn, undated (Box 3)
  - Biographical: George T. Beck, 1902-1950 (Box 3)
  - Biographical: George Brown, 1908 (Box 3)
  - Biographical: John Chapman, undated (Box 3)
  - Biographical: J.C. Nichols, 1910-1958 (Box 3)
  - Biographical: J.C. Nichols - Yellowstone Park Trouble, 1956-1963, undated (Box 3)
  - Biographical: Nichols Family/Northern Wyoming, undated (Box 3)
  - Biographical: Miscellaneous, 1902-1967 (Box 3)
  - Biographical: Newspaper Clippings, 1900s (Box 3)
  - Buffalo Bill Memorial Association, undated (Box 4)
  - Burial Investigations (includes photographs), 1980-1982 (Box 4)
  - Cody History: 1901-1913, undated (Box 4)
  - Cody History: 1921-1926, undated (Box 4)
  - Cody History: 1929, undated (Box 4)
  - Cody History: 1930s, undated (Box 4)
  - Cody History: Cody-Yellowstone Highway Project Transcripts, undated (Box 4)
  - Cody History: Legal Documents Transcripts: 1896-1910, undated (Box 4)
  - Cody History: Manuscript Sources Transcripts, undated (Box 4)
  - Cody History: Maps, 1937, undated (Box 4)
  - Cody History: Miscellaneous Transcripts, undated (Box 5)
  - Cody History: Newspaper Clippings, 1960s (Box 5)
  - Cody History: Newspaper Transcripts, undated (Box 5)
  - Cody History: Newspapers, 1960-1970 (Box 5)
  - Shoshone Irrigation Project Transcripts, undated (Box 5)
  - Wyoming: Magazine Clippings, 1927-1966 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming: Newspaper Clippings, 1950s (Box 5)
  - Wyoming: Newspapers, 1970-1980 (Box 5)
  - Wyoming: Photographs, undated (Box 5)
- Series III. Personal and Biographical Material
  - Buffalo Bill Museum, 1966-1968 (Box 6)
  - Correspondence: Personal, Research, Publication, 1962-1969 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous: Programs, Poetry, Brochures, Ephemera, 1966-1967 (Box 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings About Lucille Nichols Patrick, 1965, undated (Box 6)
  - Publications about Western Art and History, 1961-1969 (Box 6)
- Series IV. James Calvin Nichols Papers
  - Correspondence: Land Ownership and Disputes, Personal, Hunting, 1932-1962 (Box 6)
  - Legal Documents: Land and Water Rights, 1901-1949 (Box 6)
  - Lander One-Shot Antelope Hunt, 1957-1960 (Box 6)